<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Circadia</title>
<link>https://circadia.bio/publications.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://circadia.bio/publications.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Cycling reduces the entropy of neuronal activity in the human adult cortex</title>
  <dc:creator>Iara Beatriz Silva Ferré</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gilberto Corso</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gustavo Zampier dos Santos Lima</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sergio Roberto Lopes</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mario André Leocadio-Miguel</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lucas G. S. França</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Thiago de Lima Prado</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>John Fontenele Araújo</dc:creator>
  <link>https://circadia.bio/publications/ferre2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Brain Complexity (BC) have successfully been applied to study the brain electroencephalographic signal (EEG) in health and disease. In this study, we employed recurrence entropy to quantify BC associated with the neurophysiology of movement by comparing BC in both resting state and cycling movement. We measured EEG in 24 healthy adults and placed the electrodes on occipital, parietal, temporal and frontal sites on both the right and left sides of the brain. We computed the recurrence entropy from EEG measurements during cycling and resting states. Entropy is higher in the resting state than in the cycling state for all brain regions analysed. This reduction in complexity is a result of the repetitive movements that occur during cycling. These movements lead to continuous sensorial feedback, resulting in reduced entropy and sensorimotor processing.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Article</category>
  <category>entropy</category>
  <category>cortical activity</category>
  <category>EEG</category>
  <guid>https://circadia.bio/publications/ferre2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://circadia.bio/publications/ferre2024/featured.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="167" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Neonatal brain dynamic functional connectivity in term and preterm infants and its association with early childhood neurodevelopment</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucas G. S. França</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Judit Ciarrusta</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Oliver Gale-Grant</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sunniva Fenn-Moltu</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sean Fitzgibbon</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andrew Chew</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Shona Falconer</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Ralica Dimitrova</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Lucilio Cordero-Grande</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Anthony N. Price</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Emer Hughes</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jonathan O’Muircheartaigh</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Eugene Duff</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jetro J. Tuulari</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Gustavo Deco</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Serena J. Counsell</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Joseph V. Hajnal</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Chiara Nosarti</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tomoki Arichi</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>A. David Edwards</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Grainne McAlonan</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Dafnis Batalle</dc:creator>
  <link>https://circadia.bio/publications/franca2024/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="abstract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract">Abstract</h2>
<p>Brain dynamic functional connectivity characterises transient connections between brain regions. Features of brain dynamics have been linked to emotion and cognition in adult individuals, and atypical patterns have been associated with neurodevelopmental conditions such as autism. Although reliable functional brain networks have been consistently identified in neonates, little is known about the early development of dynamic functional connectivity. In this study we characterise dynamic functional connectivity with functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) in the first few weeks of postnatal life in term-born (n=324) and preterm-born (n=66) individuals. We show that a dynamic landscape of brain connectivity is already established by the time of birth in the human brain, characterised by six transient states of neonatal functional connectivity with changing dynamics through the neonatal period. The pattern of dynamic connectivity is atypical in preterm-born infants, and associated with atypical social, sensory, and repetitive behaviours measured by the Quantitative Checklist for Autism in Toddlers (Q-CHAT) scores at 18 months of age.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Article</category>
  <category>brain</category>
  <category>MRI</category>
  <category>dynamics</category>
  <guid>https://circadia.bio/publications/franca2024/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://circadia.bio/publications/franca2024/featured.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="137" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
